Guide to the Simeon Pease Folsom Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Simeon Pease Folsom papers
1840-1888
MS 947
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Correspondence and a small amount of Civil War papers of Simeon Pease Folsom of St. Paul, Minnesota and various members of his family. Included are letters from Folsom to his second, third, and fourth wives and other family correspondence. A letter from his brother, Jeremiah, describes conditions in Lowell, Massachusetts and another from E. D. Spalding discusses a small pox epidemic. The Civil War items consist of papers relating to Folsom's service with the Minnesota infantry volunteers and a map of Fort Alexis in Mobile Bay.
Folsom, Simeon Pease, b. 1819
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Herman W. Liebert, 1961.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
These are letters and other papers of Simeon Pease Folsom of St. Paul, Minnesota, and various members of his family, 1840-1888. Included are letters from Folsom to his second, third, and fourth wives, and letters to Folsom from several of his brothers, his father, his children, and from two friends. There are also letters from other friends to and from Folsom's wives. The bulk of the letters deal with family matters and news of friends, although several business letters are also included. Among the more interesting letters are one from Folsom's brother Ward W. Folsom concerning his sorrow over the dispersal of the family, one from Folsom's brother Jeremiah Folsom about conditions in Lowell, Massachusetts, where he worked, and one from E. D. Spalding about a small pox epidemic.
In addition to correspondence, there is a small assortment of invitations, receipts, and other papers pertaining to Julia (Barnum) Folsom, and several Civil War items relating to Folsom's service with the Minnesota Infantry Volunteers, Company Number 7, and the Engineering Corps. These include certificates and orders concerning his promotions and discharge, and a hand-drawn map of Fort Alexis in Mobile Bay.
These papers were given to Yale University be Herman W. Liebert in 1961. The correspondence is arranged by family member.
Biographical / Historical
Simeon Pease was born in Ascot, Canada, on December 27, 1819. He married Emeline Curts on March 9, 1846. He next married Julia A. Barnum on May 24, 1851, with whom he had two daughters. On October 23, 1860, he married Mary Gale Douglas, with whom he had a son. On October 26, 1876, he married Anna Louise Angier. Folsom died in 1888.
Education; Families; Husband and wife; Smallpox; Lowell (Mass.); Middle West; Minnesota -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; New England; Saint Paul (Minn.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Soldiers; Folsom, Jeremiah, 1780-1859; Folsom, Julia A. Barnum; Folsom, Simeon Pease, b. 1819; Folsom, Ward Weeks, b. 1824; Folsom, William H. C. (William Henry Carman), 1817-1900; Spalding, E. D.
- Inventory
  - Simeon Pease Folsom
    - 2 ALS to Julia (Barnum) Folsom, 1852 April 23, July 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 4 ALS to Mary G. (Douglas) Folsom, 1862-1866 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 6 ALS to Anna L. (Angier) Folsom, 1876, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 3 ALS from Ward Weeks Folsom (1824-), 1840-1846 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 2 ALS from William Henry Carman Folsom (1817-1900), 1840 September 17, 1852 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - ALS from R. D. Lester, 1842 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ALS from E. D. Spalding, 1843 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ALS from Jeremiah Folsom, 1846 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS from Jeremiah Folsom (1780-1859), 1850 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 4 ALS from Julia A. (Barnum) Folsom, 1851 April-September (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS from Charles B. Folsom (b. 1822), 1851 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS from Harriet O. Folsom, 1880 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - ALS from Simeon P. Folsom, Jr., 1888 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Julia A. (Barnum) Folsom
    - ALS to Caroline, 1851 March 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS to Mrs. Tinker, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS from Sarah Chapman, 1858 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - ALS from Mary Douglas, 1859 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1845-1851, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mary Gale (Douglas) Folsom: 3 ALS from Brisbin & Warner, 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Anna Louise (Angier) Folsom
    - 5 ALS from Libby Gordon, 1857-1864 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - ALS from Ellen [Angier?], 1862 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Civil War papers, 1862, 1865, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)